your true wealth is your time and
freedom money is just a tool for trading
your time it's a container to store your
economic energy until you're ready to
deploy it but the whole world has been
turned away from real money and has been
fooled is using currency a deceitful
imposter that is silently stealing your
two most valuable assets your time and
your freedom welcome to the rabbit hole
we are entering a period of financial
crisis that is the greatest the world
has ever known the wealth transfer that
will take place during this decade is
the greatest wealth transfer in history
wealth is never destroyed it is merely
transferred and that means that on the
opposite side of every crisis there is
an opportunity the great news is that
all you have to do to turn this crisis
into your great opportunity is to
educate yourself I believe that the best
investment that you can make in your
lifetime is your own education education
on the history of money education on
Finance education on how the global
economy works education on how all of
these guys the central bankers with
stock market how they can cheat you how
they can scan you
if you learn what is going on and how
the financial world works you can put
yourself on the correct side of this
wealth transfer Winston Churchill once
said that the further you look into the
past
the further you can see into the future
this program is all about creating your
own crystal ball being able to gaze into
the future being able to change this
crisis the greatest crisis in the
history of mankind into your great
opportunity
[Music]
the hidden secrets of money some of them
are hidden in plain sight they're like
right in front of you the way the
monetary system works is something that
isn't actually hidden away from all of
us it's out in the open but it's complex
and people just don't they can't see how
it works
it's hard for them to imagine that we're
living in such a hoax others are meant
to be secret but the truth is slowly
coming out like the Federal Reserve
being a private corporation and not
really part of the US government but
when I started studying this what I
found was that there was no place that I
could point people to where they could
get it all in one spot and so I
basically decided to write my book about
it and consolidate monetary history
economics the markets fundamentals of
gold and silver there's a lot of smoke
and mirrors in economics and I've sort
of made it my job to lift the fog for
people
[Music]
welcome to Egypt this is where it all
began
roughly 5,000 years ago the Egyptians
started using gold and silver as their
predominant form of currency but it was
not yet money the pieces of gold and
silver that they were using were odd
sizes and weights odd purities so it
still was not interchangeable where each
unit is the same as the next
this meant that nothing really had a
price yet we couldn't put a price of so
many coins on something because they
didn't have coins yet trade was still
difficult it was still a guessing game
when it came to the exchange of values
one of the reasons that we are in the
financial mess that we are today
globally is that people do not
understand the difference between
currency and money currency is a medium
of exchange a unit of account it is
portable durable divisible and something
called fungible fungible means that each
unit is the same as the next unit a
dollar in my pocket buys the same amount
as a dollar in your pocket money is all
of those things plus a store of value
over a long period of time even
financial planners bankers your account
they don't understand the difference
between currency and money the currency
in your pocket is a medium of exchange
it's a unit of account because it's got
numbers on it it's somewhat durable it's
portable it's divisible in that you can
make change and it's fungible a dollar
in my pocket buys the same amount as a
dollar in your pocket but because
government's can print more and more and
more of it and dilutes the currency
supply it's continually transferring
wealth out of your pocket out of your
bank account to the government and to
the banking system
the reason that gold and silver are the
optimum form of money is because of
their properties it's an easy medium of
exchange because gold and silver store a
large amount of value in a very small
area it's a unit of account pure gold
has the same value all over the planet
so an ounce of gold buys the same amount
here in Egypt as it would in China or in
the United States it's durable the same
gold that Egyptians were using in trade
5,000 years ago is still here with us
today
it does not corrode it's divisible you
can make change with it it's very
portable you could use something like
oil as money it's just that you can't
carry around a barrel of oil on your
back it's fungible pure gold is the same
wherever it is on earth
pure silver is the same wherever it is
it's limited in quantity that's the
reason that it maintains its purchasing
power government cannot print it over
the last 5000 years only gold and silver
have maintained their purchasing power
there have been thousands upon thousands
of fiat currencies currencies that are
unbanked buy gold or silver and they
have all gone to zero it's a 100 percent
failure rate
well fiat currency of course is a
currency that is exists at the dictate
or by Fiat from from a government do you
say they have their printing presses and
the paper money rolls off the printing
presses and then they give it the Fiat
designation which makes the currency
official it's just worthless paper but
when Ben Bernanke gives it to special'
sign and they have the cult meeting at
the Federal Open Market Committee
meetings it suddenly becomes currency if
you look at what's really going on it's
it's a con game and so there's
confidence well the Federal Reserve is
very forthright about what they're doing
if you read their website they'll tell
you is a competent skin they tell you
that there's no intrinsic value in their
money they'll tell you that they print
it back buy absolutely nothing they
actually display all these facts
but if you tell somebody in the public
that this stuff is created out of thin
air there's no backing whatsoever it's
absolutely worthless it's about as
valuable monopoly money they'll look at
you like you're not is there an example
throughout history of a fiat currency a
piece of paper that's unbanked buy
anything
surviving short answer no long answer no
and here's one when Addison Wigan took
over at The Daily Record I got cranked
up Bill Warner asked him to catalogue
all of the fiat currencies throughout
history what happened to eat soap
Addison dutifully went to work within a
short period of time he had gone through
the alphabet all the fiat currencies
started with the letter A we're done
they all with his news
he was halfway through the letter B at
all the fiat currencies absorbed the
letter B and there were 600 of them in
just the first letter and a half of the
alphabet and f6 what went to zero
everyone 600 fiat currencies that start
with the letter A and half of the ones
are the letter B or six hundreds of
these things that one ever came close do
you think this one United States one
after all that I don't think no no
currency fiat currencies ever survived
none
[Music]
leave up money is there actually is a
fairly well accepted definition of what
90 is the question is as you apply that
definition to particular things that are
people claim to be money do they fit the
definition we'll just take the paper
dollar for example how well does it
perform those functions well store value
the dollars lost 95 percent of its
purchasing power since the creation of
the Federal Reserve in 1913 so not very
good is a store of value one of the
things I do is just a way to get the
audience's attention is I have a slide
and there are three pictures on the
slide one is a pile of monopoly money
the other one is a pile of Federal
Reserve notes what Americans would call
paper money the other one is a solid
gold American Eagle one ounce coin and
the title of this slide is which of
these is not like the other and if you
know it shows Sesame Street or you have
children who watch it it's one of the
favorite vignettes in Sesame Street and
what it really is is a kind of IQ test
for five year olds they're supposed to
look at the three things and look at
characteristics of finding one that's
not like the other well I've shown this
slide two groups of you know Ivy League
university professors and I've also
shown their two you know children you
know kind of like resolve my nieces and
nephews and so forth and when the
professor's look if they say well
clearly the the dollars are not like the
others because the goal has no role as
money and monopoly money is junk and
American dollars of store value so
that's not like the other
but the children look at it and they say
well the gold coin is not like the other
because the other two are just piles of
paper and the gold coin is clearly
something different so my question to
the audience is who's smarter a
five-year-old or an Ivy League professor
before World War one each note that a
treasury issue would say that there have
been deposited with the United States
Treasury $20 in gold coin payable to the
bearer upon demand the money was in the
vault the currency was a note they gave
you that was a claim check only a claim
check on the money the same as if you go
to the drycleaners and you give them
your shirt and they give you a claim
check for your shirt the value is that
shirt at the drycleaners not the piece
of paper that says that you own
shuri so our currencies circulated with
the paper US Dollars and they were
claimed checked on money the next hidden
secret is the difference between
currency and money money must be a store
of value and maintain its purchasing
power over long periods of time as we
progress through this series you'll
learn that national currencies are
really a tool used by the government in
the financial sector to leech away your
time and your freedom by stealing your
purchasing power so rather than storing
your economic energy currencies leak now
compare that to the gold and silver the
Egyptians were using like I started with
it still wasn't money because it wasn't
interchangeable yet but they were on the
right track as gold and silver have
proven over thousands of years to be the
ultimate store of value gold is only
formed when a star explodes a supernova
and it stays around forever
this is one of the properties that make
it the ultimate
you know people are amazed that after
5,000 years the pyramids are still here
but what I'm more amazed at is that the
currency that the people that built this
we're using that currency that golden
silver that they were using in trade on
a daily basis it's still around today it
may have been melted down and re refined
and it's in a coin or a bar or in some
piece of jewelry but it's still with us
today and it still purchases something
yes it is the ultimate money because
there is nothing else even in the same
league it's divisible it's permanent
it's store of value it's small and unit
of account got everything you want out
of money but it doesn't go away and it
can't be increased that is what makes
goal - both beautiful money of all what
more you ask out of the money
it keeps governments under control you
can maintain a solid system governments
delight gold at present because they're
getting away with being fiat currencies
and they'll do everything they can to
discredit it as an asset class I mean my
goodness gold is outperformed the Dow
Jones Industrial Average in each of the
last seven years yet it's not considered
a legitimate asset class why again it's
the fear that maybe gold will be imposed
on the system but it will constrain
government ability to spend beyond
they can't print it to catch perch it's
not the proper definition of inflation I
use Milton Friedman's definition
inflation is an expansion of the
currency supply deflation is a
contraction of the currency supply if
you expand the currency supply
eventually prices will rise and if you
contract the currency supply eventually
prices will fall this is a pool but it's
not a pool of water this is the currency
pool and these are prices and if you
expand the currency supply prices like a
sponge in water have to rise to suck up
the excess currency government's never
stopped printing more currency and
adding currency to circulation therefore
prices keep on going up not because the
stuff that you're trying to buy is
changing the real estate doesn't change
what has changed is the currency
purchases less and less it's the
currency going down not prices going up
the truth is what we have that makes our
world work right now is a big story and
it's real it's all just promises and if
you think about it that's our currency
began to work in beginning you know
before we had currency we had barter
I'll give you three coconuts and you
give me four fish because that's kind of
a fair exchange on coconuts to fish but
they got complicated so we had to invent
this thing called money to be a
divisible portable medium of exchange
and challenges is that we've lost that a
long time ago we lost having things of
value be our currency now we have this
thing called numbers and accounts but
trust me it is not real it's a big
made-up story one of the biggest
make-believe stories ever
called quantitative ease which sounds
complex but it's really just a smoke and
mirrors term for currency creation QE
started with the banking bailouts back
in 2009 this currency was created out of
thin air
and then given to the banks who paid
themselves record bonuses and reward for
crashing the world economy this is a
global phenomena but all you have to
remember for now is that whether it's QE
bailouts or stimulus programs these are
all just booty
hocus pocus terms for increased currency
creation
I believe gold and silver will reassert
themselves as money and when they do
there just isn't enough and their
purchasing power is going to go up many
many many times
Egypt is an amazing place there's a
franticness about it utter chaos
especially like the traffic we're going
to come to like all of the merchants
that are trying to get every last dime
out of you you get fleeced to the point
where you come back with an empty wallet
[Laughter]
but you know what
they're amateurs compared to Wall Street
in the past several years I've spoken in
many countries about the crisis is
coming and a lot of people think that
they're going to be okay in their
country that it's only going to happen
to the United States or maybe the United
States and Europe but what they don't
realize is that this is a global
phenomenon I got to show you something
here this is base currency in the United
States this is the number of paper
dollars that exist basically it took 200
years to go from no dollars in existence
to eight hundred and twenty five billion
and then we had the bailouts and then we
had QE one quantitative easing one then
qe2 and then we had QE 3 and then QE
four and then soon we're going to have
QE 57 and QE 382 and it isn't just here
this is what the Canadian currency
supply looks like this is Australia
South Africa Russia now this starts out
in just the year 2001 and this is like
18 times more currency in existence in a
little over a decade
here's Singapore same story
look at that since the crisis just BAM
India China every government on the
planet is doing this insane deficit
spending and expanding their currency
supply doing bailouts and history shows
that there is no example of this turning
out well it is sometimes amazing that we
haven't experienced more inflation than
we have if they keep expanding the money
supply so vastly why aren't our price is
growing faster than they really are
and the answer is that a good chunk of
the money that the Fed created has been
shipped overseas I remember early in my
research I heard this expression that
the Americans have exported their
inflation of it when is
how can you export your inflation put it
in a box and send it what do you do well
now I understand you export your
inflation by simply sending all these
dollars that you created to these other
countries and then they send you their
refrigerators and their cars and
whatever their TV sets so you get
hardware and they get little pieces of
paper it's a great deal for the American
people for a while for a while sooner or
later all of those pigeons come home to
roost when the time comes as it looks
like it's now coming when the rest of
the world is saying we don't want to
play this game anymore Uncle Sam's
dollars are just becoming worthless
they're too many of them we've got to
find something else other than American
dollars then those dollars start to come
back to America because we don't want
them anymore what do we do with them
once this revs up and we've got this
this little trickle of money coming back
that we previously exported when once it
becomes a flood and it starts to rush
back now we are getting our former
exported inflation brought back to us
and then we'll see the quantity of money
inside the United States grow much more
rapidly even than the Federal Reserve
can create it because we're getting a
previous money back and that's when we
will really see the tanking of the US
dollar in terms of what it will buy
during the second round of quantitative
easing global food prices went up 60%
and this created a humanitarian disaster
for the two billion people on earth who
live on less than $2 a day these people
were hungry to start with that became
hungrier and some of them started
overthrowing their governments in North
Africa and around the Middle East so
quantitative easing was the spark that
ignited the Arab Spring so that's that's
it when you create money you get some
sort of inflation it just depends on
where the inflation goes
[Music]
okay given the premise that you have a
permanent underclass or poor class and
how does inflation affect them
disproportionately it affects them
basically in the percentage of their
income that goes to food and we see this
as a ratio and we know that there are
some danger points for example in Egypt
recently once that ratio got to 40
percent of income going to food and the
price of food rising due to inflation
when he got to 40 percent that's
historically a point where people
actually stage a revolution that's
exactly what we saw the French
Revolution similarly was all around the
price of food getting to a certain
critical point where people simply the
risk reward for revolution was favorable
toward revolution well exactly right
because when you have a runaway
inflation it's punishing the very people
who are most productive in society in
other words the people that produce more
than they consume and save the
difference the problem is is that those
productive people the savers save in
their national currency and
unfortunately the national currency is
just a Fiat piece of paper at this point
so when it's destroyed - runaway
inflation that $100,000 that you are
hoping to retire on doesn't exist and
the things that you are going to buy
with it and provide for others don't
exist either now what are you going to
do
so that all seems pretty scary
however you know this is going to happen
and you can only play the hand of your
dog but the great news is that gold and
silver always end up doing an accounting
of the expansion of the currency
supplies basically the will of the
public in the free markets when
governments do this kind of stuff to
their currency supply they debase it
eventually it comes back in inflation
people sense the loss of their
purchasing power they rush back to gold
and silver and they bid the value of the
gold and silver up in the country until
it meets or exceeds the value of all the
currency in circulation this is a
process that's been going on over and
over again throughout history except
this time it's happening on a global
scale it is never before happened in all
countries at once and that means that
this is the greatest wealth transfer in
history therefore it's the greatest
opportunity in history and it's not
going to happen again in your lifetime
so now we've learned that your true
wealth is your time and your freedom
money is a trading tool that stores the
economic energy that is your time and
freedom whereas currencies leak them
away gold and silver are the ultimate
money simply because of their properties
fiat currencies are based solely on
confidence and always return to their
intrinsic value of zero governments
don't like gold because it imposes
restraint rising prices are a symptom of
an expanding currency supply and gold
and silver always account for an
expanding currency supply so that's it
for this episode
join me next time as we begin to
investigate how monetary history just
repeats and repeats and how gold and
silver always win the battle between
currency and money until then my
challenge to you is to stop calling
currency money it's a crucial first step
towards setting your mind free of all
this economic boudu and changing your
context you can learn more by watching
the bonus features on our website and if
you have any questions you can post them
there and we'll answer some of your
questions in future bonus feed
so good luck thanks for watching and
we'll see you next time with this fiat
it got an Aladdin or crap desert a suit
[Music]
my camel side you're not too sure about
that I am ready for a good long nap hi
welcome to this bonus feature for the
very first episode of hidden secrets of
money and this is currency versus money
so that's the major topic